Fatih SAYIN

Austin, TX 78729 | fmsayin@hotmail.com| (512) 765 3221 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

A strategic, multidisciplinary data analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perspective. Five year of previous expertise on research and data analytics combined with the best creative data visualizations, actionable insights, and approximation algorithms available. Knowledgeable in applications of the scrum, and agile methodologies. Experience with the tools such as VBA, Python, Ipython, Pandas, SQL, MongoDB, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn, and PySpark.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Queries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Tableau

- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib,
- API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet
- Agile: Agile Methodology, Agile Frameworks Scrum

MOST RECENT PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

- Name: Machine Learning Real Estate Project (The Relationship between Stock Market & Real Estate Price)
- **Description:** The purpose of this project was to build a real-estate pricing model with a dataset which we gathered from Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT). In this project 8 popular machine learning models were used, such as Decision Tree Regression, Random Forest Regression, K Nearest Neighbors Regression, Support Vector Machine, Ridge Regression, XGBoost, Lasso Regression, Baseline Model. **Link:** https://github.com/fmsayin/Machine-Learning-Real-Estate-Project
- Name: Rental Movie Database
- **Description:** Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected. Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql challange

- Name: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects Data Analysis
- **Description:** Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign. Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables **Link:** https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel
- Name: European Soccer League Analysis
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs. GDP data set was analyzed. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed in details. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP vs teams' success.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DATA ANALYST

Cosmos Trading Inc., Austin, Texas, USA / January 2019 - Present

- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and as well as VLOOKUP function
- Created Business Intelligence (BI) solutions, analytical dashboards and tools for business users in Tableau
- Created monthly and quarterly reports in designed Excel spreadsheet with pivot tables
- Gathered business requirements and converted it into SQL stored procedures for database specific projects
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Perform weekly and monthly reviews and analyses of current processes using operational metrics and reports
- Validated resource requirements and develop cost estimate models
- · Prepared technical reports by collecting, analyzing and summarizing information and trends
- Researched, planed, recommended and implemented dashboards and data visualization in Tableau to meet the organization's business requirements
- Analyzing data from particular stock market movements. Used pandas to get stock market information for visualization

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Freelance, Austin, Texas, USA / August 2016 – December 2018

Completed some social projects as a freelance researcher and analyst

- **Used tools for all these projects:** Python, pandas, numpy, matplotlib, seaborn, beautiful soup for web scraping, Tableau, MySQL, SQL and SQLite queries and scripts, data import/export (various platforms).
- Name: Effects of failed coup attempt on July 15th, 2016 in Turkey (Prepared for Advocates of Silenced Turkey)
- **Description**: 4 million individuals indirectly affected. Analyzed the insights of the aftermath data. In this data 500k arrested, 2285 educational Institutions, 1600 NGOs, 189 media outlets and 15 universities closed.
- Name: Media Store Database for Musicians
- **Description**: Designed a database for a digital media store which is including tables for artists, albums, media tracks, invoices, and customers by using SQLite
- Name: 2016 Election Analysis for Trump vs. Clinton
- **Description**: Aggregated the 2016 election data for political results across to the US. Tried to understand undecided voters' decision for the outcome of the election by applying various numbers of statistical tools.
- Name: Refugee Migration Movements Analysis between 2000-2016 (Prepared for Advocates of Silenced Turkey)
- **Description**: Every year, hundreds of thousands of individuals get away their countries as refugees because of their country's condition. Analyzed a historical data where these refugees get away from, the country they settle in, and the potential impact on the countries accepting these individuals.
- Name: Top 10 Economies in the World 2019 (Prepared for Sustech Building LLC)
- **Description**: Aggregated the 2019 Top 10 Economies data for economies results across the World. Tried to understand the nominal GDP of the top 10 economies adds up to about 67% of the world's economy, while the top 20 economies contribute almost 81%. The remaining 173 countries together constitute less than one-fifth to the world's economy.

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Basari University Research Center, Samsun, TURKEY / September 2014 – July 2016

- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the university executive board to make the correct decisions
- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Used statistical techniques for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Analyzed academic evaluations to report to the university senate and set achievable academic goals
- Wrote academic research, made informed recommendations, managed the planning and development of design and procedures of metrics reports for short and long terms
- Led sprint reviews and monthly scrum meetings to touch base with the whole team and ensure that all members were performing successfully
- Manage project timelines and communicate with management staff, and university senate to ensure project progress satisfactorily